Guide to the Graphics collection, 1740-1995 MS2379
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Graphic collections, Circa 1891 - 1989; Series 3
  - Firenze House collection., Circa [1891?]; Series 3; 1 photonegative: glass; 25 x 21 cm. (Box 72)
    Subjects: Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 Portraits.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865. fast http://id.worldcat.org/fast/00030184; Portraits. fast http://id.worldcat.org/fast/01423831
  - The bicentennial pageant of George Washington: issued in cooperation with the United States George Washington Bicentennial commission and with its approval: twenty original etchings, each executed and signed by a distinguished American artist: with an essay on the national hero by Dixon Ryan Fox; John Taylor Arms, editor; Harry A. Ogden, associate editor., Circa [18--?]; Series 3; 189 prints: engravings; 31 x 25 cm. or smaller. (Box 74)
    Original catalog no. GRAPHIC COLL. 20
    Cataloger notes: Engravings, chiefly of political and military leaders of the U.S. Civil War era; also some earlier American political or military leaders. Most are engraved by John Chester Buttre. Other engravers include: George B. Ellis, J.N. Gimbrede, Henry Bryan Hall, W.G. Jackman, George Edward Perine, Alexander Hay Ritchie, Augustus Robin, and Hezekiah Wright Smith.
    Subjects: American Civil War (1861-1865) fast http://id.worldcat.org/fast/01351658; 1861 - 1865 fast; Generals United States Portraits.; Statesmen United States Portraits.; Generals. fast http://id.worldcat.org/fast/00939841; Statesmen. fast http://id.worldcat.org/fast/01131990; United States History Civil War, 1861-1865 Portraits. http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85140263; United States. fast http://id.worldcat.org/fast/01204155; History. fast http://id.worldcat.org/fast/01411628; Portraits. fast http://id.worldcat.org/fast/01423831
    This information was in a bibliography for the original collection 20: Engravers:
    Most of the 173 engravings in the collection were done by John Chester Buttre, who was born in Auburn, New York on June 30, 1821, and died in Ridgewood, New Jersey on December 2, 1893. He studied drawing with an artist named Hulaniski in Auburn and tried his hand at portrait-painting, with little success. He then focused on woodengraving and founded a successful business in Auburn. After moving to New York in 1841, he became well-known as a line-engraver, with much of his work during this time appearing in magazines. Later, Buttre established his own engraving business in New York where he continued engraving until his death, supposedly having completed almost 3000 plates with his name.
    George B. Ellis studied under Francis Kearny of Philadelphia in 1821 and founded an engraving business there in 1825, which lasted until 1837. He is best known for his small "Annual"plates, portraits, as well as copies of English engravings, which he did for an edition of Ivanhoe. Nothing is known about his life after 1837, as his name vanishes from the Philadelphia directories in 1838.
    Joseph Napoleon Gimbrede was born at West Point, New York, in 1820. The son of Thomas Gimbrede, an engraver and drawing-master at West Point Military Academy, he actually learned the art of engraving from his uncle, J. F. E. Prud'homme. In 1841- 1845, he went into business in New York, engraving portraits and subject plates. He then became a stationer for the Metropolitan hotel.
    Henry Bryan Hall was born in London in 1808 and died at Morrisania, N.Y. in 1884. He studied engraving in London, under Benjamin Smith and Henry Meyer. He then worked for H.T. Ryall, Historical Engraver to the Queen, to do portrait work on the plate of "The Coronation of Victoria," from a painting by Sir George Hayter. In 1850, he moved to New York, where he went into business as an engraver, as well as a publisher of portraits. Hall was also a very good portrait-painter and painted a portrait of Napoleon III in London and, while in the United States, of Thomas Sully and C.L. Elliot. He etched many portraits of men of historical prominence during the Colonial and Revolutionary period of the United States. These were done for a group of private collectors of New York and Philadelphia. Hall also painted miniatures on ivory W. G. Jackman was originally from England, but came to the United States in 1841, where he established a business in New York. He did most of his work for the Harpers, Putnams and Appletons, all New York publishers. He excelled as an engraver of portraits and subject plates, using the stipple and the line methods. Jackman also did a few portraits using the mezzotint technique for Harper & Brothers.
    George Edward Perine was born in South Orange, Essex Co. in 1837 and died in Brooklyn, N.Y., in 1885. In 1852, he began engraving for Thomas Doney in New York and in 1856-1858 for W.W. Rice, a line and bank-note engraver. He engraved in mezzotint a large plate, entitled "The Signing of the Compact in the Cabin of the Mayflower," before he was nineteen years old. He was employed by New York engravers in 1858-1860 and in 1860 began engraving on his own and soon established a successful business in New York City. He mainly did portrait engraving and though he had many engravers in his employ, it is said that he finished every plate himself.
    Alexander Hay Ritchie was born in Glasgow, Scotland in 1822. He was a pupil of Sir William Allan, with whom he studied drawing in Edinburgh. He came to New York in 1841, he learned engraving and established a sizable business. He was a skilled portrait engraver in mezzotint and also painted in oils. He began exhibiting his work at the Academy in 1848, became an Associate in 1863 and an Academician of the National Academy of Design in 1871.
    Augustus Robin was born in New York to French parents and was a skilled portrait engraver, who worked for John Chester Buttre for almost forty years.
    Hezekiah Wright Smith was born in Edinburgh, Scotland, in 1828, and came to New York when he was five years old. He studied under Thomas Doney and was a very skilled engraver of portraits in line and stipple. He was an associate of Joseph Andrews in Boston in 1850 and in 1870-1877 found employment in New York. In 1877, Smith situated himself in Philadelphia, doing much of his work there. However, he left the city very suddenly in April of 1879 and was never heard from again. His noted plates are those of Daniel Webster, Edward Everett and a head of Washington from the Athenaeum head by Stuart. The head of Washington is reportedly the best engraving ever done from this portrait.
    Subject of engravings include:
    Adams, John Quincy Anderson, Brig. Gen. Robert Andrew, John A. - Governor of Massachusetts Asboth, Brig. Gen. A. Augur, Maj. Gen. C.C. Baker, Col. Edward D. Banks, Maj. Gen. Nathaniel P. Beauregard, Maj. Gen. P.T. Beecher, Henry Ward Berdan, Col. H. Berry, Maj. Gen. Hiram G. Blenker, Maj. Gen. Louis Blunt, Maj. Gen. James G. Brittan, S.B. Jr. Brownlow, William G. Buell, Brig. Gen. Don Carlos Burnside, Brig. Gen. Ambrose E. Butler, Maj. Gen. Benjamin F. Butterfield, Maj. Gen. Daniel Carr, Col. Jos. B. Casey, Brig. Gen. Silas Clay, Maj. Gen. Cassius M. Clay, Henry - birth place Clay, Henry - younger man Clay, Henry Cooper, James Fenimore Cooper, Peter Corcoran, Col. Michael Couch, Maj. Gen. Darius N. Cox, Brig. Gen. J. Dolson Cozzens, Frederick Crawford, Brig. Gen. S.W. Curtis, George M. Curtis, Maj. Gen. Samuel R. Dahlgren, Rear Adm. John A. Davies Jr., Brig. Gen. Henry E. Davis, Com. Charles H. Davis, Jefferson Dayton, William L. Dix, Maj. Gen. John A. Doubleday, Brig. Gen. Abner Douglas, Stephen A. Dupont, Com. Samuel F. Duryee, Brig. Gen. Abram Earl, Col. Seth C. Ellsworth, E.E. Everett, Edward Farragut, Rear Adm. David G. Field, Cyrus W. Fillmore, Millard Foot, Capt. John Foote, Com. Andrew H. Foster, Maj. Gen. John C. Franklin, Benjamin Franklin, Maj. Gen. William B. Fremont, Maj. Gen. John C. Fuller, Rev. Arthur B. Garfield, Brig. Gen. James A. Generals of Our Army, 1861 Goldsborough, Com. Louis M. Governors of New England States, 1862 Grant, Lieut. Gen. Ulysses S. Grant, Maj. Gen. Ulysses S. Grover, Brig. Gen. Cuvier Hale, John P. - late U.S. Senator from New Hampshire Halleck, Maj.Gen. Henry Wager Hamlin, Hanibal Hancock, Maj. Gen. W.S. Hartsuff, Maj. Gen. George L. Hathaway, Col. Gilbert Hawkins, Col. Rush C. Heintzelman, Brig. Gen. Samuel P. Herron, Maj. Gen. F.J. Hitchcock, Maj. Gen. E.A Holt, Joseph - Senator from Kentucky Holmes, Oliver Wendell Hooker, Maj. Gen. Joseph Houston, Sam Howard, Maj. Gen. O.O. Hunter, Maj. Gen.l Irving, Washington; Jackson, Andrew Jaquess, Col. James F.
  - [Sketches for the official inaugural Presidential medal, 1949]., Circa [18--?]; Series 3; 189 prints: engravings; 31 x 25 cm. or smaller. (Box 75)
    Kearney, Maj. Gen. Philip Keyes, Maj. Gen. E.D. Kilpatrick, Brig. Gen. Judson Kirk, Edward N. Lafayette Lander, Brig. Gen. Lee, Gen. Robert E Lincoln, A. Lincoln, A. Lincoln, Abraham - early home Longfellow, Henry W. Lynch, Col. William F. Lyon, Brig. Gen. Nathaniel Mansfield, Brig. Gen. J.K.F. Meade, Maj. Gen. George G. Meagher, Col. Thomas Francis Meagher, Brig. Gen. Thomas Francis Meredith, Brig. Gen. S.A McCall, Brig. Gen. George McClellan, Maj. Gen. George B McClellan, Maj. Gen. George B. McClernand, Maj. Gen. John A. McCook, Maj. Gen. A. McD McDowell, Brig. Gen. Irvin McIlvaine, Rt. Rev. Bishop Charles P. McNiel, Brig. Gen. John McPherson, Maj. Gen. James B. Mitchel, Maj. Gen. O.M. Mulligan, Col. James A. Murphy, Paul Officers of Our Navy, 1861 Ord, Maj. Gen. E.O.C. Peabody, George Peck, Maj. Gen. John J. Pleasonton, Maj. Gen. A. Pope, Maj. Gen. John Porter, Comr. David D. Porter, Com. William D. Porter, Maj. Gen. Fitz John Prentice, George; President and Cabinet President and Generals, C.S.A. Putnam, Lieut. Lowell Reno, Maj. Gen. Jesse L. Richardson, Maj. Gen. I.B. Ricketts, Brig. Gen. James B. Roberts, Brig. Gen. Benjamin Stone Rosecrans, Brig. Gen. W.S. Rousseau, Maj. Gen. L.H. Schenk, Maj. Gen. Robert C. Schurz, Brig. Gen Carl Scott, Lieut. Gen. Winfield Sedgwick, Maj. Gen John Seward, William H. Seymour, Horatio Sherman, Maj. Gen. William T. Shields, Brig. Gen. James Sickles, Maj. Gen. Daniel E. Sigel, Brig. Gen. Franz Slemmer, Maj. Slocum, Maj. Gen. Henry W. Smith, Maj. Gen. William F. Sprague, Maj. Gen. William - Gov. of Rhode Island; Stahel, Brig. Gen. Julius Stoneman, Maj. Gen. George Stringham, Com. S.H. Sumner, Charles Sumner, Maj. Gen. Edwin V. Sykes, Maj. Gen. George Taylor, Zachary Thomas, Maj. Gen. George H. Tynge, Stephen H. Viele, Brig. Gen. Robert L. Von Schack, Col. George Wadsworth, Brig. Gen. James S. Wallace, Maj. Gen. Lewis Wallace, Brig. Gen. W.H.L. Ward, Brig. Gen. J.H. Hobart Washington, George Washington, Martha - from Stuart's picture Weber, Col. Max Webster, Daniel Welles, Gideon - Secretary of the Navy Wilder, Marshall P. Wilkes, Capt. Charles Wilson, Col. Henry of Mass. Winthrop, Maj. Theodore Wool, Maj. Gen. John E. Worden, Lieut. John L. Wounded Soldier
  - [Photographs of Washington, D.C. and vicinity]., Circa [1918]; Series 3; 76 photographic prints: black and white; 9 x 15 cm. or smaller. (Box 76)
    Original catalog no. GRAPHIC COLL. 15
    Cataloger notes: Photographs affixed to scrapbook pages (15 x 23 cm.). Subjects: U.S. Capitol, National Zoo, Mount Vernon, Great Falls of the Potomac, Library of Congress, and other scenes in the Washington, D.C. area.
    Subjects: Library of Congress Pictorial works.; United States Capitol (Washington, D.C.) Pictorial works.; Great Falls of the Potomac (Md. and Va.) Pictorial works.; Mount Vernon (Va.: Estate) Pictorial works.; National Zoological Park (U.S.) Pictorial works.; Washington (D.C.) Pictorial works. http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008117383